welcome to the stoa
the stoa is a digital campfire where we
cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge
of what's happening now
all right hello everyone and welcome to
the stoa the stoa
is a digital campfire we where we cohere
in dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge
i'll be your mc today and
we are lucky to have samwell returning
back after a two-week hiatus
with live players so the way that our
uh event is going to go today is demo
would talk for about 20 minutes
and then we'll move into a q a section
if you have any questions or comments go
ahead and put them in the chat
and during the question and answer
period you can deliver your
question directly to samo and with that
thank you so much samo for being here
thank you for having me back uh
so today i will be talking about
organized religion in particular
religion
and how it helped shape the world and
how it helped
develop civilization into what it is so
much of what i described as social
technologies and people might think of
as social technologies
might come under um the purview of the
topic of religion
right the term originates with a
language from ancient rome right
religio means meant this adherence to
behavior
adherence to proper forms adherence to
all sorts of
rituals and and social activities
um the concept of a secular state
wouldn't have made any sense at all to
the ancient romans or the ancient
egyptians or the ancient babylonians
they all interacted with it quite
differently however
uh in sumerian city-states the origin
their origin
was of these countries held as
basically you know ruled by priest kings
or at times even god kings
the official line on the pharaoh of
egypt was that this was
an embodiment of a divinity that he was
a god
not just a man appointed by gods
so that brings us to the first function
which i think is
organized religion tends to cause this
sort of
legitimization of power right
uh it's very net it's very notable that
almost
every state has needed to evoke
something mildly supernatural
be it the chinese mandate of heaven be
it again the egyptian
uh premise that there is rule by god
or gods and in the name of gods
why is this need for supernatural
legitimacy there
uh people might object and say that
modern states don't have
an appeal to supernatural legitimacy
that all they appeal to is the will of
the people as such
but i want to note that you know the
most famous example of this
uh in the united states constitution has
this
you know endowed by nato inalienable
rights by their creator right that
particular line
reveals an appeal to supernatural
supernatural principles
the classic story about this is sort of
this kind of
comptian perspective of positivism
right of this kind of view of well
there's the social utility of religion
there's the necessity for the
establishment of morals and so on
i think something much more subtle is
going on i think that
something to be considered a legitimate
power it has to feel unstoppable
so it's less about states need religion
to regulate morality and they define
themselves as
in principle always moral i think it's
more in a sense that
this state this particular way of being
this particular organization of power
is natural and inevitable and
unstoppable
so again closer to the mandate of heaven
conception
the particular thing about
the regulation also of interpersonal
morality
it's less in the establishments of
things that are right or things that are
wrong
and more the establishment of commonly
shared and recognized legible ways to
deal with conflict or to deal with life
if everyone is defining their own
morality if everyone has their own basis
and their intuition
communicating moral judgments and facts
becomes extremely difficult
one of the barriers that is filled here
is that depositing of this external
arbitration this external thing
that um absolves you of
moral responsibility or of doubt
that can regulate everyday interpersonal
interactions
very well the interesting thing about
making these interpersonal interactions
legible by making there to be
clear limits to what is and what is not
uh reconstitution for moral wrongs think
that us
things that a state might not regulate
is that it interests society towards a
higher trust equilibrium
all else equal instead of having very
local norms where you know exactly who
in the tribe
is or is not really you know
repentant for their actions you might
have something
rather simple something that could be
done in the city square
or can be done in front of many people
that allow you to be forgiven
and return into the fold or to be you
know unceremoniously cast out from the
community
make it very clear that you know you are
beyond you are beyond um
saving that there shouldn't be normal
social interactions with you
uh when the romans in their early
history wanted to declare someone an
outlaw there would be this term homo
sakura like
holy man as in this person has been
rendered onto the gods they're holy
the human laws no longer apply to them
which of course again much is the term
outlaws means that
you know killing you is not a crime
right
so the concept of an outlaw is someone
outside of the protection of the law
in an interesting way declaring someone
sacred
made them therefore in you know very
subject to a lot of danger a lot of
violence
uh that might seem so paradoxical for
the conception of religion as basically
being this thing that gives us morals
but it's not at all paradoxical if we
see it as a way to resolve
basically procedural issues or to
augment human intuitions
of violence and forgiveness and
cooperation
and modify them right introduce new
social tech
the aztecs had something very similar to
make someone a god what does this mean
like in the aztec context that means
that you would sacrifice them
right you would tear their heart out on
top of the temple of the moon or of the
sun
in front of everyone and the belief was
that the person therefore ascends
becomes part of godly nature but also
this horrific violence
is visited on them rene gerard's
thinking here
is decently important he didn't cite the
aztec example
but he did cite ancient mediterranean
human sacrifice
he had this thesis where the war
of all becomes the war of all against
one
so the hobsyan contract the habsian
paradox where
wall of war of all against all high
violence low legibility low
understanding
the hobbesian solution is that it's
resolved through the social contract of
the rule of one overall or the rule of
the community council overall
gerard would propose no it's rather the
war of all against
all becomes the war of all against one
and this person is essentially
arbitrarily chosen sacrificed
and only later do they come to reflect
on and deify the person that in the past
was sacrificed
i don't think this is quite the right
account
but gerard understands that there is a
problem there's something interesting
and unusual to explain
about the transition from very local
societies to societies that scale
from what are at times relatively
violent societies to societies that are
perhaps internally non-violent but
externally extremely violent
i think it's not unfair to characterize
bronze age societies as
internally non-violent and externally
extremely violent
in fact i would characterize the modern
nation state as being
that but more so right so in world war
one
you kill someone in you know
a fit of rage be a jealousy envy
you are tried people think you are a bad
person
you fire artillery shells at other
people at the front line not only are
you not a bad person
right firing artillery shells at people
in the trenches
you might even be a hero right you might
be awarded the iron cross
or people at home might look up to you
so there's something interesting about
this direction of violence
and this moral intuition of where things
come from or don't come from
i think that our default intuitions rely
on
this kind of very interpersonal
accounting to forgive someone
we have to personally verify them we
have to see them we have to know them
it's not really possible to smooth over
all social interactions we might trust
our judgment
to someone else say um you know my
cousin is wronged by someone
then my cousin forgives that person but
should i
forgive the person that slighted my
cousin that either
cheated them out of a deal or assaulted
them or something
like that well for that to happen there
has to be some way for my cousin to
communicate no
no i'm quite serious i'm not being
modest
i in fact absolve this person even that
simple level right this very small level
where you might imagine a few families
and so on
might require a public act well in whose
name is the public act
selected like why are people gathered
together
to say something like oh we're gathered
together in the name of this community
already quietly well the community must
have some purpose beyond itself
communities perhaps can be stores of
knowledge right such as communities of
practice or can be stores of uh
you know they can be uh stores of
resources we can communally manage
resources
but communities are never a purpose in
themselves
there's always some sort of external
purpose for their being something that
gives them legitimacy
right when we say well this community
has to self-regulate
are you talking about a company are you
talking about a university
are you talking about a social grouping
are you talking about a religious
fellowship
each of these will have a different
embedded justification
so for me to forgive my cousins uh the
person that wronged my cousin right or
the person that wronged
me if i want to make this clear to those
who might be interested in me
we already have to gather the community
and we also have to have a story of why
this community
exists in the first place why it's valid
why it's valid at all so
i think this is uh this is quite unusual
why
would we have to justify these everyday
communities through some purpose but
we actually do we do this all the time
the only partial exception i can think
of
is the family and again even
family units need all sorts of intricate
theological justification at times or
other types of justification there were
very serious arguments in early
christianity whether the correct move
is to be unmarried right and there had
to be significant debates back and forth
to say no no it is okay to be married
it's still important to be fruitful and
to reproduce
um similar debates can be found in
eastern monasticism with regard to
enlightenment
well is it even possible to practice
non-attachment if you have children
aren't children like perhaps your own
children the most
the thing that most attack you must be
most attached to right
wouldn't they be a source of suffering
aren't you exposing
them to suffering right maybe we should
just not have children
and if you look at people as purely
biological machines this kind of
question doesn't really arise
um but i think that's not quite right so
this i think possibly brings to the
third feature
the first feature is legitimizing things
by making them seem more powerful
so this is unmoving unchangeable such as
the natural law of things
gods or heaven or whatever set things to
be so
you know the creator endowed people with
rights don't ask for their questions
uh second is making social rituals that
manage the community
legible and then in the organized
religious context not only is the
forgiveness ritual
or the ostracization ritual
uh standard in a single community you
standardized it all around the
mediterranean
uh in say the late roman empire right
the roman empire actually
innovates by introducing a state
religion that is much more standardized
when it adopts christianity than what
existed before
the council of constantine makes the
roman empire christian
by standardizing what it means to be
christian previously the borders were
very diffused
and there were all sorts of syncretic
religions and beliefs and there were
other movements such as the
mithraist religion and so on that were
had comparable attraction
right and of course various
philosophical revival movements they
were much more popular
among the intelligentsia but a
philosophical movement has to have these
mechanisms of
resolution of dispute right of
resolution of dispute
so beyond those two the third one the
third really important function
um that we could give is it provides an
account of what human beings
are now you can have a secular religion
in this sense of the word you can have a
secular anthropology
that might appeal say to a more
materialist context
or a more neutral context
you might propose that okay we basically
buy the evo psych story this defines who
we are
what we're for but the act of telling
people what they are
you know they live up to it right so
it's not chemistry
it's not physics you explain to human
beings what they
are and then they do quite their best
to live up to whatever the description
you gave them
so how do you pick between several
possible descriptions of
what humans are well that usually was
the position of the official religion of
a society
or its dominant ideology i think that
the exact question as to what is a
religion and what is a philosophy is
fuzzy but some sort of supernatural
claim
is the usual distinguishing factor
i think that it's a relatively
artificial division right i think it's a
division that was
introduced partially just to end the
wars of religion in the 16th and 17th
century
so almost any worldview you can think of
for example marxism or liberalism has
metaphysical claims
embedded in it that are as difficult to
justify on purely rational grounds
as any other supernatural belief system
such as hinduism
or islam or christianity
so okay this is a good spot for
questions
open the floor great so yeah if anybody
has any questions you can just go ahead
and
type them into the chat and then i will
call your name in the order that you ask
your questions
and we can get started
so samo i'm actually kind of curious
as to your inspiration for bringing this
topic to us today
it's very interesting to me because i
feel like i've been seeing a lot of
people
start talking about institutional
religion
just in the last like few days so it
feels like a synchronicity that here you
are
bringing this to live players so i mean
um
very possible i haven't been much on
twitter but uh
these things often move very indirectly
yeah so can you what what gave you the
inspiration for this
for the subject i think it's because
it was the one relatively large area of
social technology that they left
untouched even though it's so massively
central
the three other biggest things you can
really think of is
basically formation of these sort of
state structures
and how cities work and i think i've
touched on both perhaps a little bit
less on cities than on state structures
and they have the organized religion
set up seems to be the only one that
scales
so very well right it scales better than
states even today you have
um people who are nominally in the same
religious community
and it can number it can number in the
billions
the roman state religion right or its
descendant uh
outgrew the roman empire quite a bit and
outlived the roman empire quite a bit as
well
and what are the implications for live
players
within this uh within religious
institutions
i think that i think that it's
very much the case that whenever
organized religion has a growth spurt
like a creation of a bunch of new
institutions that are supporting the
religion standardizing the religions
spreading the religion changing its
internal mechanics
changing what amounts to basically
social law right so law that regulates
interpersonal behavior and standards of
behavior
all of that stuff is requires live
player uh adaptation and change
in its absence it decays like anything
else
so you know you can still square this
with a supernatural view you could have
a view that you know every generation
needs
a new prophet with god talking to them
correcting whatever ways they've gone
often
right the old testament is very much in
favor of this because the prophets are
always these people who aren't listened
to
these people who are sort of like trying
to correct this or that
um i think the better perspective is
more along the lines that
uh i do think that
religions can be redefined fairly
flexibly
actual day-to-day beliefs are regulated
less than
outward appearances and of course
outward appearances are tied to genuine
beliefs as well
i'm not saying i'm not saying that none
of the people's beliefs change once you
come
out from christianity oh
sorry i'm sorry no problem um
i'm not saying that you know no
fundamental belief changes
but the fact is that say you might
celebrate
uh you might celebrate solstice and you
replace it with a celebration of
christmas
or you when you're trying to secularize
a country you might replace
or replace the christmas tree with the
new year tree
as happened in eastern europe but
somehow
this pattern of celebration dates of
celebration
particular practices even like you know
sacrificing
offering small offerings to stream to
spirits of streams
and trees that stuff outlived
the conversion from paganism the
conversion to christianity
by many hundreds of years it was just
practiced right both in europe and the
middle east in the 16th century the 17th
century the 18th century
it only really vanished when you moved
masses of people
well basically when when the
agricultural revolution
cut the need to have large rural
populations and you had heavily
urbanized populations
those populations recently removed from
their old physical environments
necessarily have to acquire new habits
rather than continue old habits
that changes those little beliefs right
the kind of things where a particular
stream
it might be bad luck to cross it without
doing this
or that uh local superstition that does
not change just because
you know your ruler says you are now
christian or you spoke to the right
missionary and you're now buddhist or
you know you you've been converted to
christianity
like that sort of that sort of stuff is
difficult to change
so i think because of this
outward transitions of religion can
happen far faster
than people assume they can so while the
pattern of a particular religion can be
stable
for a long time possibly just because
it's such a difficult design to get
right the geographical extent of it
the number of people attached to it
using it as the standard of
interpersonal
dispute resolution of regulation that
can change massively in a single
generation like two or three generations
are enough to completely change the
religion of a society
not its culture but just the religion of
it
great thank you paul would you like to
ask your question
well i was just interested in the idea
of metaphysical
uh propositions embedded in things that
we don't think
of the things that we think of that's
fairly
realistic um
i could i can sort of see but i wonder
if you would expand on
uh say the metaphysics of
inside of underneath marxism as opposed
to the metaphysics
underlying liberalism or other things
like that
well i think that the ideologies have
metaphysical claims now we could tease
into them
a little bit more deeply but for
starters right if we look at marxism
it's not like it's not a hegelian
ontology
it's a materialist variant on the
hegelian ontology right it starts off
hegel has this idea
that through the dialectic of thesis
and antithesis there comes always a
synthesis
and that the entire world is this
progress of idea influencing idea
until we reach the mind of god or what
he said was the mind of perfection the
state of absolute truth
which then you know he he equated with
god in some writings and
choose to not equate with god in other
writings
that transformed to there are stages of
material progress
right where material conditions give
rise to new material conditions
give rise to new material conditions
that eventually lead
to a transformation of production and
abundance beyond all measure
the implicit claim there of course is
materialism
right the that's the strongest one while
materialism is very difficult to
establish metaphysically
if you try to defeat sopsism as an
alternative
to materialism it's super hard like it's
very difficult to come up with
you know any kind of argument that
really does that persuasively or simply
sopsism being the belief that all of
this
is a dream this is just an illusion that
i have there are many people who are
effectively self-cystic
even while say claiming to believe other
things and you kind of poke into them
and you realize oh wait they are so
cystic
right they don't think any of this is
real in this metaphysical sense or
ontologically basic
philosophies would you say a sister
i'm sorry i didn't understand which
philosophies uh are so cystic
well i think i think many individuals
are very selfish i think that um
i think a lot of the people who work
very deeply
in media work and language work
might believe that all reality is social
construct and has no material construct
some of those are basically pan
psychists and believe in the reality
of thought and the reality of other
people
but others are more narcissistically
oriented
right and when i say narcissistic here i
don't necessarily mean that they love
themselves they might hate themselves
but it's more this question of is like
material reality this table this laptop
is this is this there right
um there are some people that are
committed to variants
of sopsism you could find some types of
buddhism that would endorse it
but for the most part this is like not
explicitly endorsed right
it doesn't make a good shilling point
it's not like
it's not a good protocol to interact
with others
so i think solipsism while popular i
think easily 10 to 20
of the population are so cystic usually
does not find
an organized explicit endorsed
expression
so you have kind of have to talk to a
person for a while before they
basically say that they are sophistic
i'm a buddhist i don't like that aspect
but it does seem to me to me
basically solidification
nothing that we see is really
there we're really real
right right and of course again this is
just one possible metaphysical
assumption and again that i used marxism
as an example
to illustrate how a seemingly secular
ideology does make
metaphysical claims and the metaphysical
claims are you know
if you accept the premises you can use
the premises to show that the premises
are true
and if you reject the premises it's very
difficult to show that the premises are
true
right if you don't already assume them
great we have a question from peter
would you like to ask your question
if he doesn't i can also just read the
question
um so peter says
curious to hear samo expand on his theme
of millennials underperforming at
acquiring power
possibly because of missing
interpersonal skills
i recently shared a tweet where i said
that it seems that the only type of
power millennials understand is media
power
behind this statement is of course also
the realization that throughout their
lives
as they were growing up the only right
the only kind of power they really
experienced was sort of
becoming hermione granger that is
cohering conforming being teacher's pet
appealing maybe complaining maybe
protesting
always asking an external authority that
was unchallenged
unchallengeable and far away
and the only tool you really have in
that situation be it with um
parents or teachers or your boss
is this kind of verbal manipulation so
they start to conflate verbal
manipulation to be
the full spectrum of power and they
themselves are starved of material
resources compared to previous
generations now if you look at the us
distribution of wealth you go by
generations
right now it's very heavily biased
towards older generations
no people like to simplify this and say
it's like boomers versus millennials or
whatever
but look at gen x people gen x people
have more wealth than millennials
millennials have more wealth than you
know gen z
zoomers right uh the very youngest
people
and not only do they have less wealth
because they're at the start of their
careers they have less wealth than
previous generations had at the same age
right
so so much of our inequality is age
coded
it's age distributed
because of this it's sort of like very
and it's surprisingly difficult to be
upwardly
mobile both in u.s and western society
right now so
money is mostly not a viable source of
power
and in fact money can't buy you a lot of
the things that are
most valuable not most valuable in this
feel-good way of like you know
the things that truly matter like you
know your your parents love or whatever
i mean just very very practical things
such as
how can i use money to buy my way out of
being kicked out of my own company
you can definitely you know even i think
billionaires have a certain amount of
class privilege
but anything below billionaire level can
get cancelled out of their own
organization for example
right can get pushed out either on the
work side or the anti-woke side it
doesn't really matter right
conservatives have always had their own
version of cancellation
then the next one is uh you know the
ability to
build you know physical things organize
things
organize people create new procedures
manipulate procedures i would even go as
far as to argue that millennials don't
really understand
law now law is super verbal
but it's not at the level of an
interpersonal
exchange right it's at the level of
understanding of these kind of
regulations that are distributed
plus this again practical aspect of what
does
or does not apply and what is and is not
a valid verbal argument
together with again the right privileges
right i think if
you make the exact same legal argument
as a citizen or as a lawyer
the argument will in fact be treated
differently i i believe that
it's just very difficult to try to
convince me out of it possibly
you know lawyers might be mildly
offended at this suggestion but i
believe they are definitely
they're definitely a guild that is
somewhat self-interested
uh in response to the markers of guild
belonging or lack of guilt belonging
but still this is a type of power that
you would think they would know how to
grasp but again it's not
so the only real thing that happens is
this natural advantage of interfacing
with
some aspects of digital media and some
of this aspect of
some interpersonal methods of pressure
now the key skills that i think are
missing is that i think millennials were
much more atomized than some previous
generations of people
and they've had fewer experiences of
having open
leadership positions available to them
so they've just
in terms of leadership skills and again
this is not to blame them i myself
am a millennial right it's just
objectively lower
than that of baby boomers and is
objectively lower than that of gen x
so once those older generations go away
it's not like there's a sudden
flourishing and coming into age and
coming into reality
rather it means that the new elite who
inherits the wealth of the previous
elite
it doesn't really matter for the
purposes of inequality
whether it will be the children of the
boomers or the lawyers of the boomers
that inherit the wealth that the baby
boomers hold
both are unequal societies right whether
it's the lawyers or the children
the next generation of american elites
is going to have an impoverished
understanding of what is power
what is reality how to achieve things in
other words
they will still be elites but they will
actually know how to wield far
fewer of the forms of power that are
available
meaning that in a way their control over
society will be lower which is perhaps
good
but in another way the coherence of
society and the functionality of
institutions will be radically lower
which is not good
hopefully that answers the question
[Music]
yeah definitely sg would you like to
meet yourself and ask a question
hey thanks um thanks for the
presentation
um my question is a bit generic but
it's looking at how national myths
uh sort of have come to have such a
strong um
importance you know maybe especially in
the 21st century
have they in some ways replaced uh
religious myths
in in their ability to to coordinate
mass amounts of the people
sir could you could you say that again
my my audio cut out
sure no worries um looking at how
national myths
have gained uh quite a bit of importance
and you know maybe i'm thinking is
particular in the 21st
century have they replaced in some way
the
the power of religious myths
at coordinating uh mass amounts of
people or large societies
partially yes i think just 19th century
style
nation states were significantly
uh they were digging significantly into
the same will of resources that was once
sort of the province of organized
religion i think 20th century states
also
added a story of what happens at the end
of the world
and this sort of story of why they
themselves are
the inevitable consequence of whatever
is developing in the world
so i think that yeah to some extent it's
been replaced but i think it's been
replaced through
evolving in the same direction as
organized religion
if this makes sense at least in its in
its key features right
um national school curricula in
particular
were the biggest convergence between
states and organized religions
up until you know about 1800 the idea
that you could get
all the children in the country reading
the same text
is only really achievable to a religious
authority
after that it's sort of like you know
any petty
any petty bureaucrat that uh gets on the
texas board of education or whatever
cool hopefully that answers the question
great yeah we have a question from
kermit davis would you like to ask a
question
yes thanks so uh hi salma has united
states
entered its augustan phase not in a
sense of prosperity but in the sense
that
um we're no longer a democratic republic
but pretend to be
or not and i kind of think about the
imperial pres imperial
presidency in terms of foreign policy
and then the growth
of like unaccountable bureaucrats in
domestic organizations
well i think the u.s president is
uh the emperor of japan and not the
shogun of japan
by which i mean that he has ceremonial
authority
right and everyone sort of on a gut
level if you talk to americans you
realize a lot of them think that
the president runs the country right
just on this kind of like emotional
believed level
not on the rational level though say
three branches of government and all
that
but the president is assumed to run the
country and there's a general
obsession with the presidential election
versus all the other mechanisms you
might choose to
influence government with i think the
presidency
is stronger than ever and the president
is
not weaker than ever but weaker than the
president was 50 years ago i think the
president is currently stronger
than the president was 10 or 20 years
ago
partially this is you know just sort of
the weirdness of donald trump
where as long as he can use twitter and
as long as twitter can't ban him
he has a direct method of speaking to
his followers right
outside of government this was lacking i
think people should understand
presidents did not have the ability to
speak directly to their supporters for
most of the 20th century
right it was intermediated through media
organizations
so okay there are a few minor things
pushing in that direction but still the
disconnect between presidency and
president
is vast i also think that power has been
accrued
by the supreme court and by the u.s
intelligence community at a much
faster rate than the president has if
you say compare
the us president to the u.s intelligence
community in 1950
of the president is in charge by 1960
it's almost certainly the agencies by
1980 it's not even in competition
anymore
however but the 1980s the intelligence
community fragments
almost fractally so any say
you know individual intelligence agency
might end up being weaker
but the intelligence community as a
whole like runs the country in a
relatively oligarchic fashion
i think so i would say that
we are sort of in the era of senatorial
abuses of power
there except the real senate is not
congress right
if we use the roman comparison thank you
but we have a popular question here from
shar
would you like to meet yourself and ask
us
sure um um hey good to see you
hi chris um great talk i was
i was wondering you know some people
have have
said that we should start cults i'm not
sure if you're of the same
same opinion and if so uh i guess the
term cult brings to mind a certain
anti-technological aesthetic something
like branch dravidians or whatever or
the amish
um so if we do have to start cults
what would be pro-technological
pro-social pro-expansionary
cults and what rituals can we start
thanks
right right um i think starting cults is
difficult
and i know most cults are unproductive
in the sense that they
are economically exploitative of the
membership of the cult
some smaller number of cults are
productive it was a while ago an attempt
to
you know introduce some of um
cult-like characteristics to economic
life
and i think that
i would encourage much more the reform
of cults than the creation of new cults
so in other words i think being working
with the framework of an existing
organized religion
and changing it massively probably leads
to better outcomes
and one of the reasons why i think it
leads to better outcomes it constrains
away
all sorts of terrible design choices
it also means that almost instantly you
start with some social legitimacy rather
than zero social legitimacy
i think that society as a whole is a
cult and cults don't like competition
so as soon as you are starting a new
weird strange cult
that is inwardly oriented even if it's
economically productive
it enters a pathological relationship
with the rest of society
and piercing this barrier where you're
no longer a competing organism but
you're more like the mitochondria of the
cell
right like in a symbiotic relationship
with the rest of the organism
it's extremely difficult so it seems to
me it's it's much easier
to you know try to
transform or splinter an existing
religious group
that's highly active so for example
right now i'm surprised and you know
hopefully hopefully i'm not seen as
encouraging this i'm just sociologically
surprised
that there haven't been more splinters
off of the mormon church
right it seems highly active well
organized people speak foreign languages
they're well off economically
yet they still are definitely solidly
coordinated
but but it's very you know it's very
central right
it's kind of unusual that there hasn't
been more activity there
um a different one is i think that
there has not really been a proper
attempt to leverage
the winner takes all dynamics of online
audiences
with a particular religion arguably the
closest thing that has happened in this
space are the weird mega churches of the
1980s and 90s but that's not internet
native at all
so any sort of religion which could
offer people a way to start shit posting
as if they're
members of that religion and then
eventually buying in
completely digitally and entering
virtual digitalized struggle sessions
oops i mean confession
right it's the same thing would come to
dominate society fairly quickly
so maybe the joke is well maybe such a
religion is emerging as just not calling
it
a religion but that's that's a whole
separate discussion for now
so yeah
great all right let me see so
there's a question i'm going to ask on
coleman's behalf what types of
power are underrated by millennials
and then maybe gray also was interested
in maybe tying that in
to the intersection between millennial
culture and a culture of victimhood
well i think that you know i don't
really i don't think victimhood
is chosen but it's always participated
in
so i think in a way you know i think in
a way
the fact that millennials can bond so
well
over what amounts to generational hatred
suggests that they're quite comfortable
with the world where they're not in
charge
so i think i think uh they when
millennials come to be their own
age group uh they will continue to
firmly believe someone else is in charge
even when they are in fact the person
that is in charge
i'm not sure whether a stronger overlap
can be made there
like you could you could consider
you know say advances in in various
kinds of social
norms and so on to you know
be adding to the cult of victimhood but
i really
i really don't think it's that
complicated i think it's much simpler
and then so uh you talked about so so
connected to that
so what type of power are millennials
not seeing
or not seeing themselves as uh
interested in
inheriting as the older generations
you know pass away and kind of a new
changing of the guard may happen
i think that millennials don't tend to
understand procedural
procedural power at all for example i
would expect them to
regularly make uh legal mistakes that
baby boomers would not make or
underestimate the power of law fair uh
so like you know legal warfare
compared to uh public opinion warfare
they're gonna tend to
consistently overestimate the importance
of public opinion pressure
versus something like having the board
of a company be
all of your close friends and never ever
putting
enough people on the board to actually
give you
you know enough people so that they
produce the appearance of oversight but
don't actually
you know don't actually exercise
oversight that's not a thing that i
think most millennials intuit as a
viable power move and i think most
people that are say
at least gen x age understand it as a
power move but it means
like selling out man right they consider
it bad
uh and i think slightly older people
don't even consider it bad when they
discuss it privately
um so procedural power either in the
legal variant
or the office politics variant another
one would be
i think they undervalued property it's a
little bit of a sour grape situation
but they've uh not had property for so
long
that they don't understand that no
actually you know no
actually owning owning land and
especially owning housing
is the way american society is
structured
your ticket to base to being kind of
like you know part of the welfare state
i think america has a real welfare state
and it's oriented towards homeowners
and i think everything outside of that
is like a fake welfare state
cool and another one is perhaps
possibly the value of being to being
able to produce
physical things whatever people say
they want physical things and smuggling
is always possible
so you can always manufacture something
and launder it through an intermediate
organization
and still take a significant cut for
what you manufactured
right so this this idea of doing like
physical
physical products producing things
it doesn't land naturally right so i
don't think any millennial is inspired
to be an industrialist
interesting thank you all right let's
hear from anish
would you like to ask your question
hi am i audible uh yes
okay um so
the question i had and i'm going to
mostly read it out is
um so you mentioned that um
you know in the beginning that a lot of
the stuff that we are dealing with
is like opinion uh stuff like
millennials do not seem to have a very
good
sense of such of power other than that
so
um it seems that the ability to create
or
refi or draw boundaries around local
social contexts as opposed to in a mass
media context
seems upstream of most of the issues
that
are exercising people today um do you
have any thoughts on that like will a
corrective radicalism about communal
self-protective norms
be the next development i mean we seem
to be seeing things of that kind already
happening you know look at the explosion
of private and curated spaces
like the one we are in um and um the
upsides of downsides of this
further development i mean i gave an
example of how this would feel like from
the inside
which is you know speaking about
anything that happens here to the
outside world is
uh we don't have these norms yet but i
expect there are quite a few spaces like
this out there like
if you speak about anything that you
hear here outside
we'll treat that as defection and throw
you out um
i think norms of that type are very weak
online currently
and are being actively undermined by
central institutions
so the concept of doxing someone that is
exposing their private information
for the purposes of provoking
retribution against them in the physical
world
right so taking an online dispute
physical
right that was an artifact of forum
culture and blogging culture in the
early 2000s it's not an innovation of
in fact as a social norms against it
have decayed
partially encouraged by ever bolder
journalism right
now of course i think journalism is now
weaker than ever right
uh in the sense that if the new york
times
is trying to mess with scott
of slate star codex it is because
the new york times is weak enough that
scott of slate star codex
is uh is seen as a significant uh
intellectual authority to them
like this which has just been impossible
in 2000 or 2005 or 2010 even
but still they they can't set norms they
can set what is correct or not correct
and i think most people's intuitions
that you could be
earnest and real online have been
destroyed so i feel like
a precondition for building communities
of trust
is self-trust when you are online the
idea that you could be earnest or real
in a text conversation or in video i
think this again is an idea that
predates 2010. it
comes out of a desire for authenticity
online sometimes it was paired with
cypherpunk-like ideologies right it came
from the area era of pseudonyms
and anonymity it doesn't seem like a
native idea
for people that you know have primarily
used say tik tok
or youtube or instagram for them the
online spaces where you produce
and project the perfect self image
the perfect manufactured product for the
purposes
of not being ostracized and it's kind of
a war
of all against all so if these kind of
things happen
i actually have a very pessimistic
prediction i suspect this they might
happen
in uh you know these online harassment
movements
every now and then there's something
that you know provokes harassment online
and people kind of
unify around harassment of that for a
little bit
so perhaps like a very gerardian dynamic
but even those i think have a relatively
short half-life right now
all right do you think norms will get
of this kind of like strong spaces with
very strong boundaries around them that
the
outer world doesn't even know about uh
do you think these will become more
prominent as
time goes on as you know the oh i think
i think in person meetings without
phones will start to be seen as quite
subversive and dangerous
i think like 20 years from now there
will be a report that
there will be an article in a mainstream
publication saying
the two senators met while leaving their
home phones at home
and that will be like in itself
considered mildly scandalous
like proof that they were up to no good
but i think precisely because of that
the like physical
in-person space will become you know
this equivalent of the fringe space of
1990s chatroom
right so it's almost an inversion right
nothing i write online
could possibly matter nothing i write
in physical space could possibly matter
right it's
switched over needs space and digital
space
and what is the space for the marginal
or for the
for the uh private okay
thank you
great and as we're closing up
here i wanted to go back to an earlier
question that was a little bit more
about
you samo that was from angen
so i don't know engine do you want to
unmute oh he says he wants me to ask it
on his behalf so
okay here's the question who would you
mo most like to interview in the world
today
and why and if you could interview them
in private
maybe without your phones uh is there a
preference falsification you'd most like
to try
to poke at
well that's an interesting question um
it's a long list of people i'd want to
interview um
i think that if i could speak
if i could speak chinese i think a
one-hour private interview
with xi would be extremely useful
um i probably have a lot of fun say
talking to like the vladimir putin's of
the world
and so on but i feel like i understand
it much better
and i feel like i would learn much more
about chinese culture
in terms of intellectuals i think there
are some very
there's some exceptional people active
today
uh but for nearly all of them i think
let's put this way i think nearly every
intellectual that's
active in public right now is more in
the business
of participating in the discourse than
shaping the discourse
in a strange and very interesting way xi
has
more ability to shape the discourse
because he's the head of state
of a rising society and at a massive
censorship apparatus as well
on top of that than any sort of
individual public voice can
as far as i've been able to tell if
you're truly separate from the
establishment
the maximum audience you can reach is a
few hundred thousand people
right and that's not enough to shift
society here or there so in a way
the intellectuals are like less they're
not very much the drivers of a
society right now
interesting and uh i guess we'll finish
up with a question from rachel haywire
would you like to ask your question
um what we were talking about before
about the gerardian scapegoating
and the right having its own council
culture and we're currently witnessing a
time with the harper's letter et cetera
et cetera all the
the leftists are being cancelled um what
happens when you get cancelled on the
right because
you're dealing with um straussians and
prestigious um how would you handle that
effectively
yeah it's it's very interesting like the
say the playbook for how you handle like
left cancellation is is much more
explored isn't it
um i think with right cancellation
the main effect of it is that they are
very much obsessed with positional
victories
right so particular opportunities being
denied
or particular titles being taken away
which means that as long as for example
if they
do not receive if they don't receive
if they attempt to pressure someone to
fire to fire
an individual and the individual is not
fired
but the individual later mysteriously
finds themselves in a new position
they basically like lose motivation to
pursue that target
does that make sense if a person is
fired or if a person is
denied an application that's a win if a
person is still visibly grasping for the
same position
they also consider that sort of a win if
a person goes to a different position
they don't quite know what to do with it
and they start losing coherence because
they're
the the organization is very
ad hoc and usually quite bounded in
which industry or domain it works at
they're not as good
as cross cross industry or cross domain
i see so go to this side or not the
front door or the back door
yeah yeah
all right great so we're kind of
wrapping up
here um sama do you have any final
thoughts
that you would like to leave us with
before i read
events
it seems to me that this
transition in society right we are
right now in a perfect moment for the
white collar class to start believing
new things
because for a little bit the white
collar class is at home and unsupervised
this position is only you know this
situation is only going to last for a
few months
and the only people who get to stay at
home are people who already are
exercising some amount of you know
economic surplus or class privilege or
whatever
ea essential workers are just out there
right
that's just happening um
how can you make them think if you could
make them think
or at least read you have the
opportunity for beautiful growth right
now
like whatever whatever it is you're
thinking about like whatever it is
is it a public intellectual career is it
a political career
is it a new religious or social movement
right now is your opportunity
to do something with the bored people at
home you have a captive audience
it's a great provocation
okay well thank you so much for being
here and did we decide we're going to be
doing live players every other week from
now on
uh yes great so in two weeks
come back to the stoa to see live
players with sam obrasio
and it's always a pleasure and
let me see here so what what we have
coming up at the stoa
tomorrow we have uh socratic speed
dating with myself
that's going to be i'm bumping it up a
half hour earlier so it's going to be at
30 so if you would like to come and meet
some of the people here at the stoa you
can
join me then and then we'll also have
the dark star
with pat ryan you can check out any of
our events at the stoa.ca
and if you feel inspired to give a gift
to samo
you can visit our gift economy page on
our website
i'm sure he would appreciate it and
thank you all for being here today we
see the star wars a gift and we
appreciate all of your
attention and commitment to this
community
so we will see you see you later